[Music]
Hello everyone.
Hello. And it's I'm really looking
forward to this session actually cuz
like I mentioned just before I love the
I love the practical tips and the
ability to actually get that um get
those insights from you know real world
stories uh up. Now this session you're
going to be talking about both copilot
and cursor right? Yeah. Right. Yeah.
It's not very technology. It's more a
methodology and a rex roon experience
and I'm very happy to to share this with
you. Awesome. Well thank you very much
and uh with that why don't I add your uh
slides over to the stage and the floor
is yours. Thank you. First of all, I
will introduce uh just the planning I go
fast and introduce myself and then we go
deep in the experience itself. So I work
for Xabrica. Xabrica is a small company
uh providing services around building
product technology modernization and um
consulting and of course we we are doing
AI for a long time now. And uh this
session will speak about one experience.
This is our customer many French company
but also international not very
important about me uh I'm very happy to
to share the the floor with very famous
people in this conference I'm work
mainly in France uh for learning tree I
I was a trainer for for for 20 years uh
for talis and more international I work
recently for rakuten a Japanese
uh so so on it's not very important
rakiten is important because is uh where
I I learn uh some stuff about uh AI
coding assistant and this is a story but
I I went I want to speak and not not
read this story um the idea is my main
customer for for Xabra is launching an
an AI initiative but they were stuck
last year uh with no perspective. uh the
starting anal project in uh in 24 is not
sure to to finish it before 25 and uh I
I was just starting my position and I
said that um at Rakuten we discover uh I
coding assistant and in few days we are
able to to prove that the um
productivity and the uh wellness of the
developers can be better. Uh
so this customer uh asked me to to
provide this uh a service a support
service a consulting service for his
team and six team was deployed um sim
simultaneously about 100% at the
beginning and finally it was 80 and
that's this journey I will tell uh
today. So what we do
um the idea is to to be faced to the
develop some developer pressure. Some
developer already use the tools uh in
shadow IT and also some business unit
are very autonomous in this company and
they are able to to to deploy uh all the
these new tools without the agreement of
the security or the HR or the COP. Uh so
the my customer is a CTO of the of the
corporation of the group and he want to
to manage and to to control that uh
because these tools are new uh they can
be scary uh they can uh perhaps share
some secret uh code all over the
internet. So we have to manage that. Uh
that's the the initial need is to to
control the deployment. The challenge is
to find a solution, a secure solution
and to be able to measure uh the success
or not. It was the name of the project.
It was an an experiment. Uh the idea is
to test and if it's good, we continue.
If no, we stop. And the other um
challenge was to convince the CISO the
security team and some skept skeptical
developers uh who are not very con
convinced by by these tools. So what we
did uh it's a very simple and very
methodical approach. We we we did a we
start by a strategic planning phases uh
with a a strong sponsorship sponsorship
from the Cto and the CEO was embedded at
the beginning uh and he he he discussed
with us and we he shared some uh
concerns and we try to to respond to all
these points. Uh we also plan a project
with a gradual um deployment uh not in
what on in one day not a big bang first
team we we adjust for the second second
team etc
etc another very important things of the
project it's uh the support by free
expert free AI expert uh with many
experience and for the two devops team
We also manage one of the EI expert was
um a DevOps guy. So he can talk the same
language terraform Elm. Uh and doing
cursor with Terraform is not the same to
do to playing cursor with Java orn net.
Uh we put also some channels with teams
to build a community. uh because the
expert are not available
247. Uh and perhaps the experiment uh
team can uh help itself uh every every
time when the expert are not connected.
And we also set up some um uh
ceremony to measure to in continue
continuously at the minimum every sprint
the tech lead have to repurchase uh the
result about the cut coverage the
quality gates etc etc. That's the main
project. Now we can go in deeply in
detail. So the analysis in the Jagnos
was um done by interview mean uh we we
try to to to ask why why why to identify
the pain points and we also ask what are
your current tool you you are using in
each team because it's a big company and
they use several language languages and
we have to identify the right tool um
mostly covering
uh the common uh ide utilized in in this
company. In the second phase, we we
select the tools. Uh so it was copyot
and jet brain and we we uh test but uh
we cancel the usage of continue with a
local LLM because the power of the um
laptops was not enough. uh and uh we we
go on the cloud solution. We also define
some um criterias for uh team selection.
The uh
um subject is uh to we we cannot deploy
this kind of assistant tool uh in a new
brand new team with no organization, no
metrics and no existing code because the
risk is too too dangerous. Uh I I repeat
it is an experimentation. We don't want
to to break everything. we just want to
test something. Uh so we we we should um
select mature teams with good practices,
metrics, ability to repair if something
is breaking etc etc. Uh we also um
define some technical criteria and
security criteria about all the
communication should be encrypted.
uh the we should have the
uh certification from the editor the edi
the software vendor that the security is
respected etc. uh they are already have
a contract with Microsoft of course like
many companies and uh GitLab send us um
a consulting uh software architect and a
consultant to reinsure every
everyone's and the third phase was the
uh experiment itself for six months and
we
um sorry uh we drop the number of
developers. At the beginning 100 was uh
selected but when we see the usage on
the first weeks first months uh we uh
cancel the um licenses for the less uh
motivated people. Uh uh this
was many mainly um ex externals
contractors uh not uh involved in the in
the project. So uh and it's not it was
not uh the skeptical but was people with
other over other issue in the in the
company we want to focus uh only with
motivated
people. We also during the
experimentation before start before
deploying we did we did a kickoff with
the management and all the tech leads.
At this kickoff uh the github solution
architect was here and re as I said
before reansure everyone. The team
itself was onboarded one by one uh not
the same day uh with a three or four
days uh gap between to improve the
process and to uh respond better
response every every question because
every time is the same asking etc. So we
do we did some um whiteboard with a
posted game to to define what you are
scarier of what you want to do with the
AI etc to to to to fix and to identify
what is the imagination of the everyone
at the beginning of the experience and
we did the same at the end and they they
see by themsel the gap and the the
success of the experimentation from the
beginning to the end. We um did we
propose to have one expert for two team.
The expert is very close with every
every team. He know everybody by his
first name and able to to to recognize
which language he's using. is was very
close to be also reinsurance and to be
uh confident with with the support. And
at the midterm during the after the
first quarter we also did um a midterm
meeting uh with some all the metrics and
uh a large conversation with everybody
to uh listen what is running well what
running bad and also what we can improve
in the in the support provided. So it
was very important to adjust uh at every
moment. So this is a photo of the of the
project. I already say every everything
we can see the idea and the tools we we
use. Uh I prefer to to speak about the
team. I was not alone. I speaking today
alone but I was not alone. uh there was
a delivery manager with me uh providing
all the support planning the meet
scheduling the meeting etc. the three
experts uh very good
guys and recon very popular in Genai and
France uh and I was lucky to have them
and Chural uh it's the guy from GitLab
for the kickoff session he was very
important also uh in the
project the planning uh going from
September October we start uh to to end
of
March some workshop We did also at the
the first quarter it was uh we we take
the end of each developers to help them
etc. At the second part of the of the
experiment we did also some workshop
more focus on uh topics uh some topics
was code review. How can I do a code
review with my genie coding assistant?
Okay. How can I refactor project? How
can I uh improve the unit test
generation the code the unit test and
also the the data
uh some sample of ue generation from
royal frame or screenshot uh also
migration from view 2 to roof three uh
but in the in the real code it's not it
was not a demo it the the team come with
their needs and uh the expert help them
to do that and the meetings are very
short 30 or 40 minutes. In 40 minutes
all the base code uh the code base of
Vue2 application can be migrated to a V
v3. Uh so uh it was very uh efficient
and they take in their bag uh the the
experience for the next time. We also
did a workshop about SQL and um uh
everything running around the DB uh
optimization index um com naming
commission to to rearrange a bad
structured database etc. And also so one
or two team are using PL/SQL and very
legacy code uh with old version of Java
etc. and they was very septic. But with
Jet Brain, they also um be became more
confident because they can they be able
to reverse engineer engineering the uh
the code better understanding do the
documentation and it was a good start to
uh uh
modernization. Some conclusion uh uh
benefits and lesson learned. We I did I
say we we measure everything. Uh we
tried to measure everything because some
some teams did not uh didn't play the
game every time. Uh but we can be sure
today that for 80 developer some as
every everywhere some are very good some
are middle range and other are not the
best. But in the uh meantime in the um
uh globally the productivity was
increased about 10% from five to 20. Uh
we reduce uh the time to code we can we
we can measure that more feature were uh
provided during this period. The
documentation grow the code coverage
grow from 60 to 89 85.
uh we try to be sure that the quality of
the code was not degraded. So uh every
team selected should have a sonar
monitoring active and we se we
we ensure that the grade the the
notation of the code uh was uh the same
or better. And we also measure return on
investment uh by adding all the expense
the customer paid. So the uh exabrica uh
uh fabrica presentation uh with the
project team and the expert uh the
software licenses the time invest in the
meeting and the
workshops and we uh sub We uh subtracted
the time saved and the time saved was
was um expected by the um some uh survey
we we did uh and also uh by a formula.
It's not it's not a very very strict uh
with these numbers of the about the
productivity and the reduce time to
code. So uh we define that the right um
time saved is about three error per
week. Sure. uh it's not very optimistic.
It's it's the the lower of the of the
response we have we have. But uh this
formula says that the the money we spend
here and the money we save there the the
return on invest for six months is 150.
So it's a way to re
to to say to the uh the customer that it
was a good
project. The quality uh the quality uh
is very important. Many papers are
coming out actually about um quality of
code after using the Genai tools. uh we
were very vigilant about that and we see
also um a movement from the beginning to
the end of the project. At the beginning
the developers start to use only
completion. Uh they start to use
completion and at the end they do more
um uh prompting uh to to solve the pro
problem or to write code. So it's a
completion to vibe coding. we can say
but we also notice that the the juniors
uh the low experienced developer have to
be more drive and uh because at the
beginning they accept every suggestion
of the AI coding assistant and we told
them and we insist on the fact that they
have to be critics and they have to uh
choose what they write they are
responsible of the
Um we also uh add more
uh we see some rigor about uh the
upgrade support uh but it was very
specific. No no speech. We tried to to
check and to verify the technical depth
was reduced by more documentation, more
tests and uh we improve we accelerate
some framework migration or library
migration some caution and and risk uh
we we
we face as everyone with AI to
alienation. So sometimes there was a big
bugs in the in in the code produce. So
that's why in the team selection is very
important to have a team with a CI/CD
running well and test. Um we also
um uh sensibilize everybody about
perpetual uh intelligence property and
uh security as I say at the beginning.
So um everybody working on a critical or
very sensible project was not allowed to
participate to this
experimentation about the framework
ethical framework required. We also
uh secure the fact that all the liy used
and everything use suggested by the AI
have to be approved by the company. So
we stay in the in the frame. it was not
open bar.
what we do differently uh now uh some
internal blockers were revelated as I
say at the beginning uh it was 100% uh
and then 80 because some people was not
very convinced uh by by this project and
you we have no time to to lose uh it was
an experimentation it was not changing
their life their life so we prefer to to
eliminate that And we can get we can
have one or two weeks more productive if
uh we did it before. Um the KPIs all the
tech managers tech leads saying yes we
will do KPIs for you. We all are ready
to provide the durometrics no problem.
And when we start the project, we see
that they have very many difficulties to
provide some some cap some
numbers. And
um the the
tools copilot and and cursor for example
provide some
uh metrics of usage uh and uh they was
not set up at the first days. Uh so we
we deploy and only one month after we we
look about the the usage and we were
surprised by uh some team was very uh
effective and and over
not and the next step for this for this
customer is to deploy warrite the the
solution and they they will select only
one copyot
uh because copilot did a big effort uh
on the last six months they cursor was
better far far better six months ago but
now the gap is is less even if some
people prefer always cursor
uh and we also have a platform
engineering initiative with this
customer and we will integrate uh coding
assistant and sharing the the coding
rules etc in the platform engineering
initiative
Uh so this is part of the developer
experience and of subject about AI we
have some agentic uh agentic project. So
I put here some recommendation but I say
already um everything uh in as in every
project there are early adopters but
also skeptics. Uh be be careful about
the skeptics. The early adopters can be
ambassador for the project and you have
to take care of them and also we uh we
we use them to to have an internal uh
wave of the popularity of the project.
Uh we also need and was good uh strong
sponsorship I say from the CTO the CEO
and al also the CISO. Um so that's that
and security I say also uh already I
keep some time for question for the HR
it's not a a very often subject talk uh
when you do AI code with a coding
assistant it's a good way to to for your
brand and for to attract talent because
many of um uh companies now uh is
uh trying to attract developers etc. And
if you provide propose to to to in the
job position that the uh position is
able to the developer is able to to use
coding assistant. It can be a difference
to attract the good one and the
developer are pride also to to to use it
and because it's very uh on the IP
recommendation start small measure often
u because the ecosystem is changing
every days avoid annual listenes stay on
monthly because perhaps today copy lot
is good and cursor are very good but
with open eye announcement about wind
windsurf
um
buying perhaps next month's wind surf
will be wonderful I don't know so uh if
I am a advisor for uh information
technology officer uh you have to to to
be agile and also uh the training is not
um is not the only way they have to
practice and to see demo and to go to
meetup and to do to go to conference to
learn every feature because this tools
uh category is going very fast in in the
new with a new feature. Uh and keep your
man in the loop. Don't let the the guy
alone on the screen. Uh and don't only
deploy licenses. You have to they have
to be
accompaniated. So that's all for me. I
hope I'm on time.
you listen to me.
There we go. Sorry, I wasn't on stage.
There we go. Um, yeah. No, you are on
time. Absolutely. Absolutely. Thank you
for the session. And actually, the a
couple of things. Um yeah, the the the
go with monthly versus annual um
licenses is really interesting and
actually what we do uh here as well and
and every license I buy whether it's
bolt or whether it's base 44 I always do
it as as monthly because yeah you you
literally just don't know when the next
thing's going to come out and people are
just going to massively adopt to it.
when you're think when you're looking at
large scale deployments though, so like
over across an enterprise, um is that
still an option? Can you would you be
able to get like hundreds or more uh on
a monthly or would the enterprise level
licenses force you more into an annual
um annual program? I think it can be
negotiated. Uh but the sales yeah the
sales of the editors will try to to sell
you a good price with an annual for all
the comp enterprise but you you have to
be strong perhaps not monthly but uh
just look a quarter you you can you can
engage for a quarter it can be a good
compromise to have a good price and uh
to don't be locked.
Yeah. One of the things that it really
reminded me of was security champions
programs. Um and a lot of the lessons
learned particularly with the uh with
the with the graph of you know start
with these individuals those will
naturally want to then uh share it with
others to show their progress then you
get the next almost like in in uh sort
by amount of doubt there is um is do you
have security champions programs at
XFabrica and is that a similar uh model
that you that you based it on or or or
learned from? No, no. Uh we have it's
very uh uh experimental. We are not very
organized about. Gotcha. Gotcha. Okay.
In terms of in terms of celebrating
success, how was there was there any
means whereby when when folks, you know,
did manage to achieve certain things,
you were able to reward them maybe maybe
not with, you know, anything like
compensation, but you know, nice good
gestures of of appreciation and those
types of things. There that's words we
we tell to the tech leads with all the
team. Uh all the success should be uh uh
celebrated on our side also with the
management at the mid midtime and end
time. We we do a restaurant and we
because it was a very good project. When
I did I calculate the error I was very
pessimistic but the reality is is high.
But I prefer to to to not be too
optimistic. And internally uh we saw the
difference on the faces from the
beginning the first meetings with a guy
looking about this tool scary that this
to because this tool can steal his job
and at the end that he he finds that
he's better than than the beginning and
it was very different and so we we
provide some uh kind of badge of the
team doing the best things eta etc. for
competition. It was very funny. Yeah.
Oh, interesting. And yeah, no, and
actually that's kind of similar as well
to what I've seen in the in the in
champions programs, which is which is
cool, which is, you know, it's good that
it's working in in multiple places. I
guess one thing different organizations
have um different policies I guess on
how much they want to roll out any kind
of tool. Doesn't need to be an AI tool,
could be a security tool, could be any
kind of tool. some mandate we want you
to use this tool, this process. Others
say look we would like you to use this
or this is available to you. We can
share with you um why this might be
useful to you. We think you know here
are some of the value that other teams
are seeing. Is there is there um
justification to use different you know
either of those approaches at different
times? Which would you which would you
tend to opt for?
Oh uh good question.
Um I don't I have not no good answer for
that depending of every team every
mindset. Uh I I'm not sure that by by
forcing the things it's it's working. So
we have to convince by uh pushing the
news. uh if you have a sponsorship
coming from the eye level and even uh in
the company in the communication in the
newspap not newspaper internet news you
communicate about that people the most
um uh septic and against this kind of
thing will come will come at the end so
I have no very good response for for
that yeah no I think what you kind of
said was is right it's like you you
know, you don't want people who are
skeptics to push against it even more.
So, the more you try and force someone
to do something, the more they're going
to push back as well. And I think I
think you're right in a sense of people
should people should jump onto these
because they want to. Yeah. Exactly. And
and and also because they see value in
others working with these tools as well.
And I think that's a much more healthy
giving people that option as well
enables people to have a more enjoyable
and more enjoyable role as well. So, um,
yeah, that sounds great. Um, we're
pretty much I think we're pretty much at
time. We are exactly on time. So,
Hubert, thank you very much for sharing,
uh, sharing your experiences. It's been
very, very valuable and we appreciate
you supporting the uh, the conference.
Thank you. Uh, thank you again. Bye bye.
Bye for now.